Guide to the Irving S. Olds Collection of Naval and Other Historical Prints and Related Papers 1587-1960 PR 47
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Prints & Related Papers from the Original Olds Donation, 1587-1960, undated; 17.63 Linear feet in 33 flat file folders and 6 boxes
  - Subseries I.A. Prints and Other Documents from the Olds Collection, 1587-1921, undated; 16 Linear feet in flat files and three boxes
    - Print No. 1081. Engraving, colored: "United States and Macedonian...", 1817 (Folder FF-24)
      Full title: "United States and Macedonian Frigates passing Hurl Gate for New York. Being the first British Frigate brought into the U. States during the Late War, fireing a salute as they pass'd." Artist and engraver not named. Published by P.H. Hansell Carver and Gilder No. 177 Race St. Philadela. 1817. From the Collection of Henry Graves, Jr.
    - Print No. 1082. A Broadside: "The Ship Union --- 98,...", 1814 (Folder FF-17)
      Full title: "The Ship Union --- 98, Will meet the enemy, on the first Monday in April, with an American Crew...not one fainting lubber among them. Peace, obtain'd by the thunder of our Cannon...not by base submission!". Broadside concerns the Ship Union and her commander, Samuel Dexter, and War of 1812. Yankee Office. Boston, March 1814. Used in the campaign of Samuel Dexter in 1814 for election as Governor of Massachusetts.
    - Print No. 1083. Engraved portrait: "Captain Jones Commander of the Macedonian", undated (Folder FF-25)
      Published by J. Kneass 125 Market St Phila. G. Delleker Sc. Three-quarters profile portrait of Captain Jones. Ribbon in tribute below portrait reads,"The Captur'd Frolick". Vignette. Companion to Print No. 438A.
    - Print No. 1085. Lithograph, in sepia and colored: "Combat between the Frigate Constitution & the British Frigate Guerriere.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      Lithographed by D.W. Kellogg & Co., Hartford, Ct. Print No. 143 is the same print in black & white.
    - Print No. 1086. Lithograph, colored: "The capture of H.B.M.'s Sloop of War Java by the U.S. Frigate Constitution.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      Lith of D.W. Kellogg & Co. 110 Main St. Hartford Conn.
    - Print No. 1089. Engraved map, colored: "A Sketch of the Operations of His Majesty's Fleet and Army under the Command of Vice Admiral the Rt. Hble. Lord Viscount Howe and Genl.Sir Wm. Howe, K.Brin. 1776.", 1777 (Folder FF-32)
      Published Jany. 17 1777, by J.F.W. Des Barres Esq. From "The Atlantic Neptune". References are below title. Map shows Manhattan, Staten Island, parts of Long Island, New York, and New Jersey.
    - Print No. 1092. Aquatint, colored: "To Captain H. Hope,the Officers, Seamen, and Marines of His Majesty's Frigate Endymion,...", 1815 (Folder FF-32)
      Full title: "To Captain H. Hope,the Officers, Seamen, and Marines of His Majesty's Frigate Endymion, This Print representing the Action with the American United States Frigate, President, on Sunday Evening Jany, 15th, 1815; off Sandy Hook - is respectfully Dedicated by their obedient humble Servants, J. Burr & G. Ballisat, Gracechurch Street, June 1st, 1815." Engraved by Joseph Jeakes. painted by T. Buttersworth. First of a pair of prints, see No. 1093 for second.
    - Print No. 1093. Aquatint, colored: "To Captain H. Hope,the Officers, Seamen, and Marines of His Majesty's Frigate Endymion,...", 1815 (Folder FF-32)
      Full title: "To Captain H. Hope, the Officers, Seamen, and Marines of His Majesty's Frigate Endymion, This Print representing the Morning after the Action with the American United States Frigate, President, Jany, 16th, 1815; which lasted two Hours and a half - is respectfully Dedicated by their obedient humble Servants, J. Burr & G. Ballisat, Gracechurch Street, June 1st, 1815." Engraved by Joseph Jeakes. painted by T. Buttersworth. The particulars & the position of the Ships by Lieut. Ormond of the Endymion. Second of a pair of prints, see No. 1092 for first. Same print as Print No. 326, except in colors.
    - Print No. 1095. Engraving, colored: "Massacre of the American Prisoners of War at Dartmoor Prison on the 6th of April 1815. by the Somersetshire Militia.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      W. Carnes, del. G.G. Smith, Sc. Salem, Mass. Explanation and key is printed below title.
    - Print No. 1096. Lithograph, black & white on sepia paper: "Argentine Fleet, Under Admiral Brown, Dekay Van, Espoora Rear.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      Full title: "Argentine Fleet, Under Admiral Brown, Dekay Van, Espoora Rear. Defending the passage into the inner Roads of Buenos Ayres on the 27th Sept. 1828. Against the Brazillians, Adl. Norton, his last attempt, before peace." Key of boats follows title. Lithography of Imbert NY. "No. 6" in top left.
    - Print No. 1097. Engraved portrait: "Commodore Stephen Decatur.", 1813 (Folder FF-25)
      Wm. Birch pinxit. Freeman Excudit. D.Edwin sculp. Entered according to Act of Congress, April 1st 1813, and published at Philadelphia by Freeman and Pierie, of the state of Pennsylvania. Below profile portrait of Decatur is a small vignette of the action between the "United States" and the Macedonian"naval scene with two masted ships.
    - Print No. 1098. Engraving, colored: "The Expedition against Cape Breton in Nova Scotia, 1745.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      Printed for & Sold by Carington Bowles, at his Map & Print Warehouse, No. 69 in St. Paul's Church Yard, London. Same print as Print No. 985, except in colors.
    - Print No. 1099. Engraving, colored of sepia tone: "A View of the taking of Quebec September 13th 1759.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      Title and explanation is also in French. "London, Printed for R. Sayer & J. Bennett No. 53 Fleet Street."
    - Print No. 1100. Lithograph, colored: "View of New York. From Weehawken - North River.", 1849 (Folder FF-32)
      "Palmer, Del...N. Currier, Lith. N.Y." First state. Published by N. Currier.
    - Print No. 1101A. Engraving: "Robert Fulton.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      Painted by B. West P.R.A. Engd. by G. Parker. Appears to be signed by "R. Fulton"
    - Print No. 1101B. Engraving: "James Rumsey's Steam Boats, 6th Nov. 1788...John Fitch's Steam Boat, Dec. 1787. See Rittenhouse's Certificate, page 1075...Robt Fulton's Steam Boat, The North River or Cleremont, 1807.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      "From a sketch by Joseph Dyer. Pubd. in Woodcroft's origin & progress Steam Navigation" "Engraved & Printed by Gavit & Duthie."
    - Print No. 1104. Etching: "The Takeing of Miss Mud I'Land.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      Print shows a female figure as the Mud Island fortress, Fort Mifflin, with two flags on her bonnet, astride a cannon firing on the British warship "Isis"; also show the "Somerset", "Roebuck", "Eagle", and the "Vigilant" of the British fleet at the confluence of the Schuylkill and Delaware rivers. Refers to naval action off Mud Fort in October 1777. From the Harris D. Colt Collection.
    - Print No. 1105. Woodcuts: "Commodore Oliver Hazard Perry." "Perry's Victory on Lake Erie, September 10th, 1813.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      Woodcut portrait of full face portrait of Perry, signed by J.W. Orr, N.Y. On the back is text from page 146.
      Woodcut, colored, of Perry's victory is signed "Barber Sc" and "page 287." is to the right of title.
    - Print No. 1107. Sheet of Engravings: "Essex & Alert. Aug. 13 1812." "United States & Maedonian. Oct. 25 1812.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      Two circular vignettes -- one showing the masted ships, Essex & Alert; the other showing the masted ships, United States & Macedonian. The "Essex & Alert" print is same as Print No. 974.
    - Print No. 1108. Engraving: "A View of the Fort & Harbour of Oswego from Lake Ontario Representing the Attack by the British on the 6th of May 1814.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      T.H. Wentworth, del. Illustration from "A Gazetteer of the State of New York," by Horatio Gates Spafford, Albany, 1813.
    - Print No. 1109. Engraved portrait: "Paul Jones The Founder of the American Navy.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      No artist or publisher given. Appears to have engraved signature, "John Paul". Three-quarters profile portrait.
    - Print No. 1111. Lithograph, colored: "A Brief Sketch on the Principle Events in the Lives of William Henry Harrison, and John Tyler, with Splendid Ornaments by Benjamin Owen Tyler.", 1840 (Folder FF-32)
      Designed, written, and published by B.O. Tyler, Albany, NY. "Lith by Baker, 8 Wall Street, NY...F. Grennell, pinxt. Troy." Elaborate poster-sized lithograph with center article of biographies of Harrison and Tyler. Top piece with eagle and banner, "The march westward of Empire takes its flight." Decorated columns down each side. Center bottom vignette of Harrison residence in Ohio.
    - Print No. 1112. Engraving, colored: "Combat Mémorable entre le Pearson et Paul Jones...", undated (Folder FF-25)
      Full title:"Combat Mémorable donné le. 22 7bre. 1779, entre le Capitaine Pearson commandant le Sérapis, et Paul Jones commandant le Bon-Homme-Richard et son Escadre." "A Paris chez Mordhare et Jean rue St. Jean le Beauvais No. 4."
    - Print No. 1118. Lithograph, colored: "American Historical Portrait Gallery of Eminent Characters in Our Own History.", 1856 (Folder FF-33)
      30 portraits of Emminent Characters in Our Own History. Published by A.H. Jocelyn, N.Y. City.. 1856
    - Print No. 1121. Engraving, colored: "Vue de New York. Prise de Weahawken. A View of New-York, taken from Weahawken.", circa 1834 (Folder FF-32)
      Ambrose Louis Garneray, pinxt. Engraved by Sigmund Himely. Published in Paris by chez Basset. Published about 1834.
    - Print No. 1121A. Engraving, (facsimile): "Vue de New York.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      Artist signed [Ambrose Louis] Garneray. [Prise de Weahawk...Paris, 1834]
    - Print No. 1124. Aquatint, colored: "To that distinguished Nobleman from whose Precepts & Example the British navy has dervied its present unrivalled state of Discipline and Glorious Preeminence John Earl of St. Vincent, K.B....", undated (Folder FF-32)
      Full title: "To that distinguished Nobleman from whose Precepts & Example the British navy has dervied its present unrivalled state of Discipline and Glorious Preeminence John Earl of St. Vincent, K.B. late first Lord Commissioner of the Admiralty, Admiral of the Red. Lieut. General of the Marines, etc. - This View of the Commencement of the Action between His Majesty's Ship Shannon and the United States frigate Chesapeake, off Boston Light House on the 1st. of June, 1813 is respectfully Dedicated by his Lordship's obedient Serv't. G. Webster." Painted by John Theophilus Lee Esq. Engraved by Joseph Jeakes. Published by G. Webster & Co., London. Sold by R. Lambe.
    - Print No. 1127. Drawing, colored (water color): "Ships at Sea.", 1798 (Folder FF-25)
      Signed "George Gustavus Lennock" "Aug. 5th 1798" Scene of four masted ships; two are flying the British flag.
    - Print No. 1128. Partial Broadside, colored: "Captain Broke & His Brave Crew Boarding & Capturing The American Frigate Chesapeake, Off Boston, June 1st. 1813.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      Below colored drawing is a poem entitled, "The Shannon and Chesapeake; Or The Rival Frigates." "Written by Mr. Ingall, and sung with unbounded Applause by Mr. Sinclair, of the Theater Royal, Covent-Garden." The broadside is attached in some way to a backing with some form of accounts.
    - Print No. 1129. Silhouette: "Constitution.", 1862 (Folder FF-25)
      From label on back: "Made by an old sailor on the Constitution and presented to my father in 1862." Brown paper silhouette mounted against light blue paper.
    - Print No. 1130. Engraved map, colored: "A Plan of the Operations of the King's Army under the Command of General Sir William Howe, K.B. in New York and East New Jersey, against the American Forces Commanded by General Washington, From the 12th of October, to the 28th of November 1776.", 1777 (Folder FF-32)
      Map by Claude Joseph Sauthiers; engraved and published by Wm. Faden, 1777. The engagement on the White Plains, the 28th of October, is particularly distinguished.
    - Print No. 1134. Engraved sketch: "Sketch of an Attack - Made By - Majr. Genl. Jackson, on a Division of the British Army commanded by Majr. Genl. Kean on the evening of the 23 Decr. 1814.", undated (Folder FF-25)
      The sketch features the Mississippi River and the locations of the American and British troops -- related to the Battle of New Orleans.
    - Print No. S1200. Lithograph, colored: "Battle of Buena Vista.", undated (Folder FF-26)
      Full title: "Battle of Buena Vista. Fought February 23d. 1847._The American Army under Genl. Taylor were completely Victorious." "Lith. & Pub. by J. Bailie, 88St. Near 3rd. Aven. N. York." Notes on how many fought, killed and wounded on each side.
    - Print No. S1201. Lithograph, colored: "Washington's Reception by the Ladies at Trenton, N.J., April 1789.", undated (Folder FF-26)
      Full title: "Washington's Reception by the Ladies at Trenton, N.J., April 1789. On his way to New-York to be Inaugurated First President of the United States." E.B. & E.C. Kellogg, 136 Main St. Hartford Conn.
    - Print No. S1202. Lithograph, colored: "American Homestead Summer.", 1868 (Folder FF-26)
      Published by Currier & Ives, 152 Nassau St., New York. [Peters no. 2315.]
    - Print No. S1203. Letter: "Robert Fulton to David Cooke, Pittsburgh.", 1814 October 15 (Folder FF-26)
      MS letter, 4 pages, dated October 15, 1814.
    - Print No. S1204. Engraved map, colored: "Planiglobium Terreste Minus in hanc formam reductam a Johanne Bapt. Homanno Geogr. Excudente Christop Weigelio Noribergce.", 1724? (Folder FF-26)
      Geographer/artist is Johann Baptist Homann. Christoph Weigel, engraver. [Nuremberg, 1724?] World is in two hemispheres. Circular insets at top and bottom center show Polus Arcticus and Polus Antarcticus. [Cf. Phillips, List...1909, no. 568]
    - Print No. S1205. Engraved map, colored: "Novi Orbis sive Totius Americae cum Adiacentibus Insulis. Nova exhibito.", 1724? (Folder FF-26)
      [Geographer/artist is Johann Baptist Homann][Nuremberg, 1724?] North & South America, with illustrations allegorical cartouche on lower left corner. {Cf. Phillips, List ...1909, no. 568]
    - Print No. S1206. Lithograph, colored: "American Homestead Winter.", 1868 (Folder FF-26)
      Currier & Ives, 152 Nassau St., New York. [Peters No. 2316]
    - Print No. S1207. Lithograph, colored: "The Catterskill Fall, at Catterskill Mountains.", undated (Folder FF-26)
      Currier & Ives, 152 Nassau St., New York.[Peters No. 4113]
    - Print No. S1208. Engraved map, colored: "Wight Island [England].", [1676?] (Folder FF-26)
      Described by William White. Published by John Speed, London. [1676?] Inset maps of Southhampton, and Newport. Plate from Speed's Atlas, with text on reverse side, and list of towns. Phillips, List ...1958, no. 5949, no. 8.
    - Print No. S1209. Engraved map, colored: "Americae Sive Novi Orbis Nova Descripta.", 1587 (Folder FF-26)
      Cartographer Abraham Ortelius. [Amsterdam] North and South America, with large & elaborate cartouche in lower left corner. Faint handwritten note in pencil on back.
    - Print No. S1210. Engraved map, colored: "Novissima et Accuratissima Septentrionalis ac Meridionalis Americae Descripto, multis Locis recentibus aucta et correcte divisa in Omnes Partes Hodiernas per Fredericum de Witt, Amstelodami. Cum Privilegio D.D. Ordinum Holl. West Frisiaeges ex Officina P. Mortier.", 1706? (Folder FF-26)
      Cartographer - Frederick De Wit (1616-1698). Amsterdam, P. Mortier. [1706?] Map of North and South America, large illustrated cartouche in lower left corner.
    - Print No. S1211. Etching portrait: "E.D. White", 1912 (Folder FF-33)
      Signed by "Schneider" Copyrighted 1912 by William H. Baimore, NY. Inscription reads: "Irving S. Olds, Esq. with the esteem and warm regards, E.D. White".
    - Print No. S1212. Print from Copper-Plate: "Oliver Wendell Holmes to his old friend Irving S. Olds.", undated (Folder FF-26)
      "© Charles Bannon" - Top left corner. "Eleventh print from copper-plate [signature - not legible][Franklin Wood]
    - Print No. S1213. Photograph: "Group Portrait of Supreme Court.", 1921? (Folder FF-26)
      Harris-Ewing, Photographers, Washington, D.C. 9 Justices from left to right: Oliver Wendell Holmes, Willis Van Devanter, W.M. Harlan, Horace Tinker, E.D. White, Charles E. Hughes, Joseph McKenna, J.R. Lamar, Wm. R. Day (signatures below photo).
    - Print No. S1214. Lithograph, colored: "A Home in the Wilderness.", 1870 (Folder FF-26)
      Currier & Ives, 125 Nassau St., New York. [Peters No. 1540]
    - Print No. S1215. Lithograph, colored: "The Mill-Stream.", undated (Folder FF-26)
      Currier & Ives, 152 Nassau St., New York. F.F. Palmer - Del. [Peters no. 2417]
    - Print No. S1217. Broadside: "Lands for Sale to Actual Settlers.", 1802 (Folder FF-26)
      Jason Torrey placed the advertisement and Miner's Press-WilkesBarre published the advertisement on April 19th, 1802. Lands are in Wayne County, Pennsylvania.
    - Print No. S1218. Broadside: "Rates of Toll. for 20 Miles of Road.", 1802? (Folder FF-26)
      Toll rates are listed for every animal, cart, chair, carriage, etc. Notes along the margins. Above the title pencilled in, "Bethany & Kingman's Choice Road."
    - Print No. S1219. Broadside: "To Adventurers. The Completion of the Delaware & Hudson Canal, has opened a wide and promising field for enterprise, to the Farmer, the Merchant, and the Mechanic.", 1830 (Folder FF-26)
      Jason Torrey is the subscriber. W. Sasman of Bethany, Pa., printed the advertisement on June 17, 1830. Offers lands in the villages of Honesdale and Bethany for actual settlers, sites outside the villages for Manufacturers and Mechanics, and farms.
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "Stephen Decatur Esq. of the United States Navy.", undated (Box 3)
      Three-quarter faced portrait in a small round frame.
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "Stephen Decatur Esq. of the United States Navy.", undated (Box 3)
      Three-quarter face portrait in a small round frame. Appears to be same portrait as above.
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "Isaac Chauncey Esq. of the United States Navy.", undated (Box 3)
      Full face portrait in a small round frame.
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "Isaac Chauncey Esq. of the United States Navy.", undated (Box 3)
      Full face portrait in a small round frame. Appears to be the same portrait as above.
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "William Bainbridge Esq. of the United States Navy.", undated (Box 3)
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "William Bainbridge Esq. of the United States Navy.", undated (Box 3)
      Full face portrait in a small round frame. Appears to be same portrait as above.
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "David Porter Esq. of the United States Navy.", undated (Box 3)
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "David Porter Esq. of the United States Navy.", undated (Box 3)
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "James Monroe President of the United States.", undated (Box 3)
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "Geo. Washington Esq. Late President of the U. S. of America.", undated (Box 3)
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "Major Genl. Winfield Scott. of the United States Army.", undated (Box 3)
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "Major Genl. Winfield Scott. of the United States Army.", undated (Box 3)
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "General Pike. Late of the United States Army.", undated (Box 3)
      Three-quarter face portrait in a small round frame.
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "Isaac Hull Esq. of the United States Navy.", undated (Box 3)
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "Oliver H. Perry Esq. of the United States Navy.", undated (Box 3)
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "Jacob Jones Esq. of the United States Navy.", undated (Box 3)
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "Robert Fulton Esq.", undated (Box 3)
      Three-quarter face portrait in a small round frame
    - Round Portrait: Engraving: "The US Frigate Constitution, Isaac Hull Esqr. Commander Capturing His B.M. Frigate Guerriere...(unreadable).", undated (Box 3)
      Small engraving of two ships in battle placed in a small round frame.
  - Subseries I.B. Papers Related to the Collection, 1923-1960; 1.63 Linear feet in three boxes
    The subseries holds documentary material related to the Olds print collection. These include index cards with Olds's remarks made in connection with slide presentations about his collection during the 1950s, galley proofs of his catalogue for the Grolier Club exhibition (1942), catalogues of Olds's collection (1951 exhibition at U.S. Steel, 1952 collection as of that time, and the 1959 Peabody Museum exhibition), labels taken from the prints when they were unframed, and various print matter, notes, and typescripts. The subseries also holds a photograph album and catalogues related to the exhibitions of Evelyn Foster Olds artwork, which was based on images from the Olds's collection, at the Peabody Museum and the Smithsonian.
    The subseries is arranged by subject matter.
    - Remarks by Olds in Presenting Slides of His Collection (7 folders), 1953-1960 (Box 5, Folder 1-7)
      Presentations at: Pocumtuck Valley Memorial Association, New-York Historical Society, Maryland Historical Society, Caxton Club, Friends of Peabody Museum,New Jersey Historical Society, and Metropolitan Museum of Art.
    - Labels from Backing (and other related documents) of Framed Prints, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Catalogues. Exhibition at U.S. Steel (2 copies), 1951 (Box 6)
    - Catalogues. Olds Collection (2 copies), 1952 (Box 6)
      Post-1952 Olds catalogue supplements are not in the collection, but are available through Bobcat. Call numbers NE215.U5 O53 1952 Suppl. 1 and NE215.U5 O53 1952 Suppl. 2.
    - Catalogues. Peabody Museum (2 folders; 4 copies), 1959 (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
      Holds 4 copies of the catalogue and initial letter and proposed checklist from the Peabody.
    - Catalogues. Grolier Club Exhibition (4 folders), 1942-1951 (Box 5, Folder 11-14)
      Holds 3 copies of the galley proofs of the catalogue, an annotated copy of the galley dating from circa 1948 done in preparation for a possible revised catalogue, and a list of prints in the exhibition that were not part of the Olds Collection (list prepared in 1951).
    - Notes concerning the Eugene H. Pool Collection of Captain James Lawrence, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Documents from Raoul Gerard, 1949-1953 (Box 5, Folder 16)
      Holds a manuscript (illustrated) and typescript essay on the "Stars and Stripes", a reprint of Gerard's "Illusion and Truth in History" inscribed by the author, and marketing material for Gerard's "Flags Over South Africa."
    - Typescript of "Biographical Sketch of Alexander Macomb" from the June 1842 "U.S. Military Magazine", undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Various Notes (3 folders), undated (Box 5, Folder 18-20)
      Draft checklists, object descriptions, and lists of prints to be photographed.
    - Index Cards of Bibliographical Sources, undated (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Documents, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      Holds 2 photographs of a model ship (possibly the "Constitution") and a naval-themed cartoon by Dang (1938).
    - Print Matter. Antiquarian, 1923-1924 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      Volume I, Numbers 2-6.
    - Print Matter. Nautical Research Journal, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      Volume 8, Numbers 4 and 6; Index to Volume 8; Volume 9, Number 1; Membership List of 1956 for the Nautical Research Guild.
    - Photograph Album., 1958 (Box 7, Folder 1)